this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
I see radio is brought to you by the
IEEE computer Society by IEEE software
Magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Gavin Henry and today my
guests are Peter Wyatt and Duff Johnson
Duff is the CEO at PDF Association he
has founded and led several software and
services businesses in the electronic
document industry since 1996. he also
serves a PDF industry in technical roles
as the iso project co-leader uh the U.S
tag chair for both ISO 32 000 the PDF
specification and ISO project leader for
ISO
14289 he is currently the U.S head of
Delegation to ISO TC 171 se2 don't worry
listeners I'll put those in the show
notes Peter is the CTO at PDF
Association and has been actively
working on PDF Technologies for more
than 20 years he is project co-leader of
iso 3200
1000 sorry co-chairs of PDF Association
PDF twg I think the working group and
this PDF association's principal
scientists leading work on the DARPA
funded safe docs project which is at the
intersection of cyber security parsers
and electronic document formats Peter
and Duff welcome to software engineering
radio is there anything I miss in your
bios that you'd like to add thanks for
having us Kevin and now my bio is good
thank you that sounds good Kevin thank
you excellent so we're going to start
off with a re-introduction and I'm going
to split the show up into four topics
rather the wonderfulness of PDFs these
are the history of PDF what a PDF is
made up of how to create a PDF on the
big one PDF Security on the big one I'm
calling it that it might not be so let's
start so the title of our show
is obviously 30 years of PDF
pizza or Duff could you take us through
the key Milestones over those three
years if it's possible so maybe I'll
start let's begin a little bit before
PDF so obviously 30 years is a long time
ago PDF was founded in PostScript which
was an interpreted programming language
released in 1984. so back in those days
computing power was obviously much less
things were much harder to debug and one
of the issues that people found with
PostScript was that you couldn't get to
page 100 in your document without
processing Pages 1 to 99 first and this
obviously became a problem as Laser
Printers came into fashion and we needed
to reprint Pages or you wanted to print
in reverse order or something like that
now PostScript is a fully blown
programming language it has all the
power of a programming language and you
can do very fancy things like Define
redefine white to be black but you also
need programming skills and debugging
skills in order to write a PostScript
program
so this is obviously not a great outcome
for for the graphic arts industry or
just documents in general so then John
Warnock who was one of the Adobe
co-founders in 1990 wrote well-known
paper known as the Camelot white paper
and at that point he he noted that there
were a hundred commercially available
printers and about 4 000 applications
that produce PostScript so remember this
is back in 1990. this is the days of
your 640k 286 or 386 PCS with VGA
screens so it was a very different world
than we have now and what he described
in this Camelot white paper was
something that he called IPS or
interchange PostScript but it's what we
would come to know as PDF
anyway Adobe eventually published PDF
1.0 in June of 1993 and they continued
publishing this until PDF 1.7 in October
2006.
all these versions are freely available
and it's effectively defined the format
as they saw they owned the format and
they led the development of its
direction and obviously their
implementation uh closely matched the
spec or you know effectively was the
spec
in PDF 1.4 which was December 2001 there
was actually a big sort of transition in
the PDF Technologies uh this was the
introduction of transparency and
advanced blending so this is in the days
of of early uh illustration programs
that basically these features were sort
of becoming the core features that
graphic artists were using to create
really sort of Rich marketing documents
and so forth and all these later
Concepts were actually introduced
directly into SVG from its their PDF
Origins and the features that you see in
PDF are exactly the same names that you
see in these common applications in 2007
Adobe passed PDF 1.72 ISO the
international standards Organization for
Fast Track adoption and this is a
special process by which an existing
specification can be made in
international standard in in 18 months
you might ask well well why is ISO why
not some other standards body well
because at that time there already been
about seven years of experience in
publishing what we know as pdfx where
the X means exchange and these are
standards specifically in the graphic
arts and Commercial Printing space
designed to make Commercial Printing
much more predictable and reproducible
across vendors across different devices
Etc and this had been in place since
2001 so in 2007 it was seen as it was
the obvious place to continue to take
PDF standardization
in 2008 after the 18-month Fast Track
ISO published the first PDF standard
which is ISO 32 000 part 1 2008 and it's
effectively PDF 1.7 it's very similar
but not quite identical to the Adobe PDF
1.7 version because obviously the
proprietary details and their
implementations
specific stuff was removed and if you
remember this era this is sort of you
know the mid-2000s we had a lot of
competition in in the sort of operating
system and business space from the likes
of Microsoft with their new operating
system which was code named Longhorn
and they had a new format that they
called the XML paper specification or
XPS
and there was a push to standardize that
so in a way Adobe met the challenge and
brought PDF out from behind the Adobe
wall and into the open up until 2007 it
wasn't an ital standard no it was an
adobe it was a freely available document
but it was their proprietary knowledge
and you anyone could go and download the
PDFs back and you could implement it but
it was written I guess they probably did
their best go at writing a document that
gave an open and honest understanding of
what they thought PDF was but certainly
as somebody who was involved in
developing pity of Technology at that
time there were certain struggles with
the document
in trying to sort of mimic what the
Adobe Technologies were doing but it was
freely available so although it wasn't
an international standard it was freely
available
okay was that Microsoft's attempt to try
and thwart PDF becoming a standard do
you think they had a heads up or
no I think it was in those days there
was a you know remembering back to these
days there was a you know XML was the
latest and greatest thing and there was
certainly marketing promoting that you
know XML was was better than everything
and if you do remember there was a lot
of push to to make XML the center of the
universe in those days for all
Technologies that's right yeah the
schema definitions and everything
exactly exactly so in those days the XML
paper specification it mirrored what PDF
was and XPS still exists today inside
the operating systems and used as a
spool format and you can save as XPS and
Windows 10 and 11. I don't know how many
people use it arguably not that many but
certainly at one time Adobe even
prototyped well at this time they
prototyped a version of PDF in XML that
was code name Mars not unsurprisingly it
never gained a new traction because
realistically there was no benefit in
the XML version actual fact there were
disadvantages was much larger and more
complicated and it was exactly the same
as PDF in terms of what you as an end
user saw in your documents anyway I'm
going to jump forward a little bit so in
2017 so this is remember nine years
after that first standardization of PDF
we finally published our ISO finally
published PDF 2.0
and this is the first PDF standard that
was fully developed in an open Forum
with input from many experts from around
the world and across many vendors
and this is the document we refer to as
ISO 32000 part 2 2017 Edition now nine
years is a long time even in ISO
standards time but the the result of
that work was was a vastly improved
document
it was a lot of people looking at the
document very carefully it's making
concrete suggestions and of course there
are new features that was introduced in
in PDF 2.0
but it is a the latest version
in 2020 however we we published an
update to the 2017 mainly to to correct
various points and right now there's a
process to address some errata
um about this point I might hand over to
Dart for maybe Gavin you have some
questions yeah I was going to ask stuff
actually about where the PDF Association
fits in with um the Azure standard or
you know it's raw and ensuring PDFs
lives well as Peter's been saying so the
the iso standardization process for PDF
initiated more or less around 2000 with
the development of pdfx
and the next ISO standard develops
pertaining specifically to PDF was PDF a
or the archival subset of PDF this is
published as an ISO document in 2005.
and it was received with great Fanfare
in for example Germany which is a
place of many laws and many software
companies particularly interested in
meeting the needs of the state and other
actors in terms of these laws
and in fact many of the initial pdfa
implementers were German companies so
many of them had gotten together and
been working on this new specification
and come to realize that they needed to
develop some additional industry
understandings about how to fully
understand the pdfa specification there
isn't just
PDF ISO standard there's subtypes of
PDFs so yes so as Peter mentioned uh in
2000 the graphic arts industry has had
come to a need to develop a a its own
common understanding of specific a PDF
in in the context of a specific
application that is to say high quality
high-speed print operations
so back then the the graphic arts
industry had come up with requirements
that included color management and the
include and the inclusion of fonts
directly into the PDF file as a means of
ensuring the conveyance of of a fully
reproducible results between printing
systems for example right yeah so
everything you need is bundled in rather
than so everything you just bundled in
and it turned out that the archival
community has a very similar requirement
right so these folks need a a digital
document
once created to be reproducible and and
usable as it was created many years into
the future and on many different systems
not only the the Computing system on
which the document was created so
requirements are actually relatively
similar to those of graphic arts but not
identical
and as a as a reaction to the the need
of archivists for a a preservation
oriented PDF file this is why the iso
Community or the the developers engaged
with the iso community at this point
decided to develop PDF a for archive
so the PDF Association emerges from that
because the initial set of non-adobe
developers who were producing pdfa got
together realized that they it was very
important of course that their
implementations avoided colliding
right because if you're if you're making
something that you call archival and you
and you're specifically making calling
it archival because it can be exchanged
between implementations then it's not
going to help you very much if somebody
makes one of these files and somebody
else's implementation cannot read it so
the the uh this group of vendors got
together in Germany and and created a
small organization they called the pdfa
competence Center
and the pdfa confidence Center was the
was the Forerunner of what is today the
PDF Association for the first three or
four years it ran a couple of
conferences it created some various
technical notes that reflected the
common understandings of those vendors
developed and then starting I think
around 2010 the organization decided to
expand its scope and become really the
international organization to address
all matters of of interest to PDF
technology in general
thank you before I move us on to the
next section of the show
are there any key moments in that
history that we have mentioned or you'd
like to really highlight that changed
industry or you know spared
or the e-document
businesses out there you know hello sign
DocuSign all those types of things I
think I think one of the and I think
Peter did mention this that one of the
things that I I often emphasize is that
adobe did two amazing things very right
back in 1993. and and these at the time
today these things are not particularly
remarkable but in a way they're not
remarkable today because Adobe did them
back then and the first thing that adobe
did was to make the Adobe Reader free
software
so that it was not only possible to
create a PDF file using adobe's paid
software but then anybody could read it
on any platform back then it was
relatively unusual to give away powerful
software for free for use on the desktop
so this is one important innovation and
the other of course is to publish
specification publicly with the express
intent of allowing third-party
developers to develop their own PDF
implementations creation and consumption
both
and these these two moves you know
indicated that adobe understood that the
the purpose of this technology was to
was to Take On The World of paper and
the only way to Take On The World of
paper and papers predominance in the the
business and communication space in the
world was to was to eliminate the
possibility that the that the
understanding of how to use the paper
and the soft and the software to use it
would be a barrier right so that's so
making the the specification free and
the viewing software free has has become
a kind of a Hallmark of AOL and it was a
certainly led to PDF success and I think
you know Downstream from that we see a
whole world of Technologies where the
modern era it's presume that many
software specifications are going to be
freely available and people very
commonly expect that viewing software
will not will be free whereas uh
creation software perhaps might not be
yeah I suppose they understood that to
make it successful they needed math
adoption didn't they yeah I wonder what
the industry or what format if any would
have won if they hadn't done that or
we'd still be in the wild west of trying
to print and then preserve things well
indeed Adobe did and I think we'll we'll
talk about this uh yeah there were
numerous other competitors at the time
and I think PDF was very much the right
technology that came along at the right
time it met the the oncoming internet it
met the obvious need to use a digital
means to be able to convey structured
information or laid out information and
avoid the necessity of printing and
sending thing through the overnight mail
and so on and so the the the emergence
of of internet technology met the
development of PDF very very neatly to
give people a means of conveying their
business processes from printers and
scanners to Simply emailing content and
other digital means of distribution
thank you so that was a really good
overview sort of bite-sized chunk of PDF
history I'm sure we could do quite a few
shows on each one of those subparts
everyone will have used the PDF opened
it or clicked print PDF or exported as
PDF at some point in their lives whether
as a user or as a developer it could be
spent some time taking us through what a
PDF format is so for example
those of us that are curious when they
go to a website we usually right click
that web page and click view Source you
know or try and open up a PDF and a text
editor or you know console based text
editor
why doesn't that work and you know what
are the main bits for PDF
okay well I think maybe we need to start
and say well what is a PDF so so what
it's representing as Duff said is is a
document and specifically a paginated
document why is that important well
obviously in the HTML world we can have
infinitely scrolling pages and and very
long pages but in a PDF document
everything is paginated
it's also what we call typeset and and
laid out precisely and so typeset means
that the kerning and the choice of
glyphs and the choice of typeface and
exactly and precisely how the author
wants is encoded into the PDF format PDF
is not a a format that word wraps
depending on you know the size of your
browser you have page size whatever that
may be A4 or letter size or whatever it
can be postage stamp and then the
content is laid out on that page and it
paginates and it's very precisely
defined in terms of how the appearance
model works and I mean very precisely
because you remember it's it's history
is back in the printing days in in the
the laser writer days so you know 300
dots per inch because of its I think
it's it's history and print
it's always had this definition that's
been about Precision so for example uh
you know how you dash a line is is many
pages of the PDF spec to finding exactly
how you should Dash align what end caps
to use and and all the mathematics
around stroking and filling line ends
and so on and so forth it's quite
surprising when you said it was
difficult to pick a page to print that
kind of shocked me a little bit Yeah
well if it's a programming language I
guess it's the same thing sometimes like
I'm trying to think of an analogy and I
guess today you sometimes get that if
you load a very large document into an
office suite application and you quickly
scroll to the end sometimes you have to
wait for the application to kind of
catch up you know I'm talking like 100
page document obviously back when PDF
was was starting that slowness was
Amplified by the fact that computers
weren't as powerful there wasn't as much
memory
so the ability of PDF to be what we call
a random access file format so you can
jump to any page in a PDF very very
quickly and there is no cost to doing
this you don't have to understand what's
on page one and two and three to get to
page 100 you can go straight to page 100
and display page 100 because it's uh it
has its own definitions
now having said that if your document
has the same logo on every page or the
same font on every page you can reuse
those assets so that the file size is
optimized but you don't actually have to
understand exactly how page one was was
laid out and where exactly the word
break was so you can then do page two
and exactly where that word break is and
then do page three
and if you think back to the early
versions of of office applications it
was fairly common that if you shared a
an Office document or somebody else on a
different platform you could get
different word wraps at the end of pages
and and you would have a document that's
five pages and somebody else has a
document who's four pages or it breaks
at this point in your document but at a
slightly different point in somebody
else's document
and PDFs focus on
capturing the type setting and precise
definition of the laid out document so
this is why it's sometimes referred to
as a final format but PDF isn't really a
final format it's it's just a a fixed
layout format it's not a flexible format
like your listeners would know about
with with HTML for example
so answering your other questions about
binary and text so PDF is not a text
format yes it's keywords and and many of
us aspects are defined as ASCII bike
sequences so human readable but
technically speaking it's a binary file
format because it uses byte offsets to
locate objects in the file
everything in a PDF file is is object
based and you we build up this document
object model
again a term people familiar with HTML
would know but remember this dates back
to 1990 so the document object model in
PDF is object based you can reuse these
objects across Pages or however you wish
and each object can be randomly accessed
very quickly you don't have to read the
entire file and again this is slightly
different to HTML or HTML where you have
to read you know all the tag nestings
and so on and so forth to understand
with PDF you don't have to do that you
can literally open a document and jump
straight to page 100 and have never
looked at anything to do with any other
page
naively I always thought way back I
could just grab some text out or open it
up and replace bed tags but now I
understand why that's not possible yeah
now so actually if you want to focus on
that kind of thing so one of the other
things when we talk about text a lot of
people instantly think Unicode now
Unicode is a text encoding and it allows
you to express you know very rich
character sets and so on the PDF is
actually a typeset language and
expresses the appearance of that text so
the classic example that I give is the
word office in English o double f i c e
so in some cases this can just be four
glyphs you can have an O glyph so a
glyph is the appearance of the character
the the glyph of the letter O there may
be a combined ligature for the letters
ffi where maybe the the horizontal
stroke of the FF and the I are all
joined together so you have a single
ligature representing three Unicode
characters and then the C and then the e
and so in in PDF the the author has
decided that this is the appearance they
want to give to their document and and
therefore they they Define this with
glyph IDs whereas in Unicode you would
say it's the the O the F the F the I the
C and the E and then text shaping
algorithms or text shaping software
would then decide oh you're using such
and such a font and your preference is
this and therefore you might get a
linkage or you might not
so it's kind of different things for
different courses and hence why in some
cases yes you can open a PDF file and
you can see the text and then other
cases you can't of course modern PDF is
all compressed as well which doesn't
help the text searching side of things
yeah that makes more sense now because I
remember what Duff mentioned about
preserving how it looks and bundling
fonts
the times when you open a PDF it only
works on Windows or Adobe Reader or an
open on Linux it's just horrendous and
you can't even read it because it's
obviously bundled in or linked to
if that's correct some OS font operating
system font yes and and PDF in the in
the early days I I know one of the
lessons that PDF has learned over the
years is the importance and especially
now that computers are bigger and faster
and storage is cheaper is that the the
cost of missing fonts is huge you not
only get a you know a potentially a bad
appearance especially if you're reading
a document from a from a different
language that can be a very bad
experience in life but with embedded
fonts encapsulating them inside the PDF
file then you guarantee that the root of
your document just has exactly the same
experience that the author intended
and one of the things that PDF allows is
a concept called subsetting of fonts you
don't have to put you know the the
entire aerial font for every Unicode
character you can just pick the glyphs
that you used in your document and you
can subset it and just write that small
amount of data into your file and and
just send that along with your file so
this would explain the file size
difference in a PDF you know if you were
to get a
proof of a business card or a website
mock-up done and as a PDF that can be
quite huge
or a text-based one could be you know
kilobytes it all depends on what's in
being embedded yes so primarily it's
it's the fonts and and sometimes also
obviously images because PDF is a I
don't want to say print Centric format
but at least a format that had its
origins in print then 72 DPI images and
96 DPI images with lots of jpeg
artifacts never look good when printed
so a lot of PDF software will you know
use higher resolution images and even
though you might be viewing it on a
computer screen it doesn't know that you
don't want to print it and hence the the
images are also probably much higher
resolution than you might otherwise see
on a website
okay thank you is it possible to create
a compliant PDF in a text editor so the
answer to that is is yes you have to
obviously so so in sort of the technical
workshops that we run and often if you
read the PDF specs you will see what we
call fragments of PDF and and they just
look like programming code in in a
language that's PDF basically so yes you
can do it in a text editor but as I said
the key point is that in the file
there are file offsets but so byte-based
offsets to the start of each object and
obviously if I open it on one operating
system with one set of line ending
characters and open them on a different
one then those line ending characters
can make a difference to the byte offset
so yes you can do it but you have to be
very careful and you need to know what
you're doing so unless you're a PDF
person please don't do it or you will
break your PDF file yeah from an
education yeah from an education point
of view you can do it and often many
developers getting it started and PDF
will do this as a you know a way of
learning yeah I saw some competitions
where people are trying desperately to
get the PDF size down to like half a
kilobyte or something you know if you
skipped out this bit of the spec or
either went to version
1.4 or version 1 or something and it all
opened fine you know which is a
testament to you know what the PDF
Association looks after and the
standards and everything well well
actually not it's actually it that is
often a testament to the flexibility of
PDF processors and they're willingness
to ingest PDF files that have all kinds
of interesting problems
right so as Peter said what well it
might be possible to hack yourself a PDF
file manually
it's it's a it almost it's really almost
never done except for purely educational
purposes because the the I mean this
file is counting bite offsets
the chances of really getting this right
particularly with any more sophisticated
content or very very relatively
difficult to achieve
certainly is a practical matter into
your to your comment about those kind of
challenges you you often see online and
they're more about
um what you might call the difference
between what the PDF specifications say
a PDF file should be
and what a real PDF file that's accepted
by PDF software can be and we'll
probably cover this later on when we get
down to security because obviously over
the years there are many PDF files have
been created that do have errors in them
you know sometimes it's as simple as a
typing mistake a programmer did in in
some program years ago that then was
used to generate you know a couple of
hundred million PDFs and bingo that
problem isn't a problem for everybody
who opens that PDF file
so it's uh it's a problem that we face
because our format is persistent we
often talk about persistence and as Duff
said the pdfa format is is about these
records these archival long-term
preservation requirements where that the
long term means you know 50 or 100 years
from now not just next year or
and that's a real challenge to to solve
that problem yeah some really
interesting points about the archival
format and I'll put some shoe notes in
there one of the next tools I'm doing is
about
the archiving of software so software
Heritage I think it'd be a nice uh thing
to explore in that show as well about
serving things in PDFs well just
actually just to promote something from
the association we're currently working
on a on a standard for using PDF as an
archival format for emails and obviously
there's
especially in the US there's some famous
cases of you know emails being recovered
and so forth so one of the things that
we can do is we can build on top of pdfa
the archival format and we can build
additional features specific for for
Industries such as email archiving which
have unique requirements such as you
know retaining the headers and
understanding what's there and so
actually you know we have a liaison
working group in the association
currently specifying what we call email
archiving excellent I'll I'll get a link
in the show for that that moves us
nicely on to the next section which I've
called creating a PDF but we can easily
talk about reading a PDF as well so by
the sounds of it they've been quite um a
journey of versions which as I
understand you can still open all the
versions and new versions today
absolutely you can open a PDF 1.0 file
from 1990 in software today and it will
still work that's awesome but as a
Creator what version do you pick do you
just take what your printer or software
application does or participant depend
on the industry you're in you know what
sort of advice have you got on that are
examples okay well I think there's a few
points there so I think as a user of PDF
if you're just consuming PDF or even
providing PDFs to customers you don't
pick a pdf version just like you don't
pick an HTML version when you visit a
website most likely what you'll pick is
a series of features that your document
needs now maybe this is you know the
ultra high compression so that'll be the
latest standards or some certain digital
signature feature or some encryption
feature and again that'll be later
standards and if you want multimedia or
interactive 3D content again sort of the
rare effect video features then you'll
have to pick certain features so I don't
think you really pick PDF versions what
you do is you pick the features that you
want to express your content in and then
that kind of defines the feature set
that you might use so the features
aren't tied to impression
1.7 2.0 they're all backwards compatible
so there's only maybe a very few and I'm
talking like three or four features in
the history of PDF that have actually
been removed from the standard and one
of the key things that we do in the PDF
standards committees is to focus on
backwards and forwards compatibility now
what do we mean by that so backwards
compatibility is if I was to open a
document from the future in today's
processor what experience would I get so
I encounter a new a new image format or
a new type of font what can I do to make
the experience in in Legacy software
relative to the version the PDF better
so it's it's a focus that maybe other
formats don't have but in PDF it's
certainly a very important Focus that we
do discuss a lot about when we make a
design choice to implement new features
how we can do this in a sort of a
backwards compatible way
so that would be an example of
I'm stuck on an old version of
Mac OS or Windows I've got Adobe Reader
or you know whatever readers bundled and
I open a PDF creator today and there's
no way that reader
understands the new version but it still
opens it okay yeah so I would hope a
couple of things I would first hope that
the reader checks the version number
that's in in a PDF file just like those
version numbers and many files and would
maybe present you with a warning message
saying hey we only support say PDF 1.7
this is a PDF 2.0 file
you know maybe you should use some
different software so first thing it
should give you a heads up or it
certainly has the capability to give you
a heads up that maybe this display
you're about to see is not as accurate
as it might otherwise be
but in some cases you might then get you
know either slightly different colors or
you know a different display but you
know hopefully as a human you'll be able
to interpret enough of the document to
to achieve whatever it is you're trying
to achieve thank you and is it easier to
read and display a PDF press versus
creating a PDF so so obviously
that's a very hard question to answer so
the PDF specification is a lot about the
display of PDF so yes a lot of the text
and PDF is about how it displays the
creation side is really coming down to
libraries and and so forth and sdks that
you might use and certainly there's a
ton of Technology out there that can
take you know an HTML canvas or an HTML
content and just convert it to PDF and
assuming that that software is of high
quality then it will carry across what
we call the semantics of that content
you know it can know that the headings
The Heading and the paragraph the
paragraph and this is a bulleted list so
all these sort of semantics can carry
across in PDF that's why I'm trying to
get to is you know move us on to
programmatically
creating and reading if you're using an
SDK that's maybe not so up to date or
not been so well written then the same
content can be generated but maybe you
lose all those semantics so yes the text
is still there it's selectable text I
mean I guess the worst case would be
software that takes something like an
HTML page and converts into one very
large image now it still is a human you
you look at the PDF file on the screen
and it looks exactly like you would
expect but you can't select text you
can't search for that text and it's not
a great experience I have seen PDF like
that actually we try and copy and paste
the text on PDF and it's that's an image
well obviously scan to PDF you know
especially since you know the fading
phasing out of fax machines and you've
got to remember that you know if faxes
have come and gone in the time that PDF
has been around
so scanning of documents used to be a
big thing it's still a big thing in
certain industries especially for for
the archival community where they have
to capture you know digitize a lot of
documents to to uh replace paper with
with digital records
so there are specific features in PDF to
support for example scan documents and
and OCR text and all this kind of thing
but you know if you're creating what we
could call a digitally born document
then realistically you shouldn't be
having that experience you should be
having an experience with with text
content that's extractable searchable it
captures the semantics that are at least
in your Source document now maybe your
Source document is nothing more than a
text file and therefore has no semantics
but if it's an Office document and
you've got style sheets and headings and
paragraphs and bulleted lists then all
that should really be captured over into
the PDF and PDF has all these features
and has had for many many years
so really to go back Circle back around
to your question I think a lot of that
really depends on the libraries and sdks
that people use and really maybe that's
the key advice we're giving to listeners
here is don't just accept the first
library that converts content but spend
a bit of time trying to understand that
is is the PDF that's been created of
what we would call high quality and I
don't mean visual quality I mean kind of
semantic quality and how would you
validate that just based on what you're
trying to achieve there is ways I mean
obviously that the first thing is
obviously to check its institutional
appearance but don't just use one viewer
and make sure you check across all
platforms make sure that text can be
found that you can you know find and
search and replace the technon replace
but search for text in your document uh
ensure that the metadata is up to date
if you're creating something that's
probably going to be a record so I'm
thinking things like an invoice or a
purchase order or something like that
which is typically kept in a
organizations document management system
for for many years maybe not for
hundreds of years but at least for you
know 10 or 15 years for the tax law
reasons or whatever
then you should probably look at PDF a
as a standard and pdfa has a lot of what
we call validating software so software
that can run over the top of a pdfa file
and check to make sure that all the t's
are crossed and all the eyes are dotted
and it's a good quality file and it
really is obeying the good quality rules
that archival PDF requires tough just a
couple of questions about the
PDF Association
do you guys maintain a list of
recommended libraries or you know what
Peter just said there about
linting or validating PDFs that we could
link to or so the PDF Association
actually very specifically and
deliberately does not do that the
association is a meeting place for PDF
developers to come together to discuss
proposed features issues of concern
requests for clarifications to allow
different Industries to find common
understandings so for example we have
working groups that are specific to the
engineering space where we have folks
who are thinking about 3D and Aerospace
to manufacturing who are very interested
in in how 3D and other kinds of related
models can be can be Deployable in the
PDF context and as Peter mentioned we
have other working group working on
email archiving using PDF and so on so
what we're what we do specifically do
not do is get into the business of
trying to pick winners and losers from
within then the developer community that
supports the world's PDF implementations
and what were one of the reasons for
that is that there are so many different
means but but the larger point is is a
member organization
our our job is is not here to sit in any
way in between the consumer and the
developer we would we would probably
have relatively few members if we were
around in the business of characterizing
our members products right instead we
provide really a platform for them to
talk and for them also to Showcase their
products but we're we're not uh you know
internally there may be and within the
the members only discussion groups there
may be arguments about this or that uh
the other interpretation but we're not
here as a sort of uh as the PDF police
if you will okay thank you the reason
why I ask is because as our listeners
will know depending on what programming
language they they use whether it's
something that's put upon them because
of their job or you know their chosen
language
in my experience as well you find a PDF
library that does maybe you know 70 of
what you're trying to do and then it's
been abandoned or
it's been developed to meet the needs of
what that developer wants so I'm just
trying to figure out you know to
navigate some of these sdks of who you
go to what are the recommended ones you
know how you
review them and say yeah this is pdfa
grades that's you know almost at the
spec or what have you I think for the
for the what we call the the subset so
these are the pdfa and the pdfx variants
on PDF you will always be able to run
validators because they exist and
there's lots of software out there that
can can check that for you
in terms of general purpose PDF so just
the PDF that we as consumers send around
to each other or maybe you know receive
or download off a website that's a
harder problem but I guess the good news
is PDF has been around for 30 years you
should definitely be using a maintained
library and if nothing else that just
goes to the security discussion we'll
probably have soon but there are PDF
libraries in in all the languages and
even you know very very newish languages
you know go and Swift and so forth there
are very capable PDF libraries around
and many of our members do participate
in these forums to try and help people
understand the PDF spec it is a 1 000
page specification it's not a a light
read by any sense
you know we do a I guess as an
association do promote
people to join us and have the
discussions understand especially with
things like a rata and uh we have a
public GitHub repository where people
can report issues or misunderstandings
about spec and we're here to help people
understand well this is what that you
know part of the text means and this is
how you can do it yeah I've reviewed
some of your GitHub repos that I think
you both have so I'll put those in the
show notes and as I presume there's a an
Implement implementer type group that
developers could potentially join to ask
questions or something or forum
that supported or is it really for
developing the spec so there are there
are a number of different forms within
the PDF Association many of them are
Members Only
in that so the association among its
other responsibilities it maintains the
ISO standards development process
so we are we are the managers of iso
tc171 and C2 which is the subcommittee
responsible for the development of most
of not absolutely all of them but most
of the PDF specifications formats and
and subsets
and we do it and we as we we have an
employee uh Chief technical officer and
former Peter we have a number of
different uh things that we do to
service the industry so kind of that we
we then have a kind of the our spaces
that we operate for meetings consists of
both member only forums or in the
development of the specification and for
other subsets and for sort of Industry
discussions but in addition we operate a
number of liaison working groups which
are intended specifically for
interfacing with non-members who have
specific vertical requirements or or
cases so I mentioned engineering and
Manufacturing another example would be
email archiving group and another
example would be concerns pertaining to
accessibility
so we we also work in fact there we have
numbers of groups that are working on
developing improving the interaction
between PDF and the assistive technology
that's characteristically used to help
folks suffering blindness and other
disabilities to be able to to perceive
and to read PDF documents but we also
work in the you know these liaison
working groups occur in also the print
product metadata space so we have a
variety of ways for it for developers
who have an interest in the subject here
we have a tangential or other need it's
actually a common thing for us to
receive an inquiry hey out here in the
world we're trying to do this thing with
PDF how could the association support us
and and sometimes those are inquiries
you know we can't do anything with them
and other times they result in the
development of a community which is uh
constructed in precisely to support that
process I'll give you an example the law
Tech folks who develop the type setting
system for which runs much of the world
scientific publishing they came along
and said well we we're looking to
develop uh uh to improve the way in
which we create PDF files from latex
that would include all the semantics
said in the tagging and so on allowing
disabled users
to view scientific publishing
Publications that are written with latex
and so as a result we created a liaison
working group that would allow folks who
who are working specifically on law Tech
development to come along and
participate in our discussions and then
significantly to allow PDF Association
members to join into that discussion so
that and that's really what we do we
provide that interface between the
people who have questions and then the
people who really know PDF very deeply
thanks stuff that's a great overview
I'll make sure I get um some point to
contact in the show notes as well for
those types of Developers I'm going to
summarize the last two sections just to
confirm
my understanding and then move us on to
last section of the show just to keep us
on track so PDFs is a binary based
format where the layout and other things
that are important to the create of the
PDF are either embedded and that's not
just the text and the words that's
exactly how the Creator wants it to look
the version of the PDF depends on what
features you want as a Creator to be in
that PDF
but a reader
will then know instantly what version
the PDF is and understand what it
supports and where it can display for
you depending how that PDF is created I
could use my text editor but it sounds
pretty impossible
and given the fact that the show is 30
years on PDF you should review and
expect the libraries and sdks of your
chosen programming language to be pretty
capable
but there are some validators and
limiters for the PDFs that I'll get some
names off both of you offline and make
sure they're linked to in the show notes
I think that's a good summary would you
say creating a PDF and what's involved
in it yep I think the other aspect that
maybe we should talk about too is we've
talked about creating the PDF but
nowadays a lot of websites and other
experiences have a PDF viewing
integrated into them and this is
probably the one place where the 70
completed just doesn't work anymore when
rendering a PDF file and displaying it
on the screen or on a piece of paper you
really do have to be 99 or better in
terms of completion
um and and this is where sometimes
people can be fooled if you have
software that's less capable then you
can look at the same PDF on different
platforms and see very different things
because one maybe one software can't
display a certain image format but after
30 years realistically speaking I I
don't think there's really any excuse
the software that's being used there is
is clearly very old as I said who's the
embedded sort of JavaScript PDF display
no no I mean that particular one is
actually really really good no no what I
mean is some of the other ones maybe you
know less maintained open source
software but the rendering of the PDF
file is the most important thing and if
you if you do search on the web there
are uh test Suites you know commercial
test Suites as well as a few open uh
Source test suites available where you
can grab some PDF files and you can see
exactly you know does my viewer for
example uh show what we call annotation
so so PDF has this feature like your
office documents where you can review
and mark up a document you know
strikeout text highlight text all that
kind of stuff but you can do it in a PDF
file now many of the old viewers don't
do this but all the new viewers and all
the mainstream viewers uh should be
doing it because there's really no
reason not to be doing it yeah I
experienced that same thing exact thing
on Friday one of them one of my podcasts
gas marked up
the show in an article for IEEE and he'd
use the comment thing it didn't work on
my Google Mail preview and some other
things but it did work and you know one
of the big name creators my viewers
rather
it just it downgraded nicely like you
explained and said it would it just
turned the comment into a little voice
box icon you couldn't do anything with
it but you could see there was something
there so it it was backwards compatible
that way yeah and I should actually add
the PDF specification only specifies the
file format and very few what we call
processor requirements on software so a
lot of those sort of experiential things
um are actually not defined in the PDF
spec and again I I think this is a bit
of history but it does allow people to
to innovate and create different types
of software and you only have to I think
look at you know an iPad experience from
a from a traditional PC experience and
you can see you know a fair variety of
different experiences with PDF but all
based around the same sort of feature
set of the file format
as a creator of that PDF you need to be
conscious of where it's going to be
consumed in red ideally you shouldn't
have to be but if you happen to know for
example that your users will be on you
know their phones or something then then
yes you should but that probably also
goes just as much to things like the
choice of page size you know whether
it's uh the American sized papers or the
or the you know A4 European style paper
sizes there's other sort of aspects as
well so
if you were to create a modern file now
and we talk about semantics now one of
the things that I've spoke about just a
few minutes ago was the importance of
semantics now semantics today is used in
many applications for their ability to
Reflow a PDF so although PDF is a fixed
file format a lot of software nowadays
has the capability to take a PDF and
refit it to your appropriate screen
because
we're not all on desktops anymore we do
have phones but exactly how that works
that is not in the in the PDF spec so
that is kind of a layered feature that's
been added on top by the vendors in
being creative to to address I guess
some of the challenges that paginated
content faces in the modern world
thank you so we've touched upon
bundling things with PDFs and that will
bring us on nicely to PDF security just
share with us some historic security
issues that have been with PDF and a few
examples and what's been done about that
since
yeah I guess we you know we need to
recall the history discussion that
opened up the podcast you know PDF 1.0
was 1993 and it was well before security
and devsecops and all this kind of thing
were front of mind so
or even considered in any way it was a
long long time ago
now having said that I think certainly
one of the things that I find most
amusing with PDF is really The
Accidental information disclosure from
users you know typically governments and
um
lawyers or something who forget or just
don't know how to redact the document so
redaction is where people think about
putting you know blacking out some text
so that you can't see the name of an
individual or something like that
but you know hopefully as people have
learned from this this discussion we've
had today that PDF is made up of these
text objects these graphic objects and
these image objects so putting a black
box over some text doesn't make that
text magically go away you actually yeah
I was just going to say that based on
how you explained it before that's just
an object on top of a correct so yeah as
a human you can't see it anymore in the
rendered appearance but if you do a text
extraction on and the classic case is a
journalist will do a copy and paste and
paste it you know take the content and
paste it into their notepad or something
like that and bingo all the supposed
redacted words reappear I'm sure you
your listeners can remember lots of
famous cases where this kind of thing
has happened but no one seems to learn
their lesson and it really is a source
of amusement and amazement it continues
to happen and PDF actually has a
full-blown reduction workflow as part of
the file format where you can go through
official I want to say military grade
but a proper regimented process where
people can redact content and then you
can classify what you know the reason
for the red action then you can approve
the redaction and it's all built into
the file format so then at the end you
can publish a document that's truly
redacted including things like you know
portions of images or or people's faces
and photos all this is possible on PDF
but unfortunately people seem to just
put the black rectangle over the top and
ship out the PDF and regret it yeah one
of the first things I do on a PDF just
for fun is to file properties and look
at all the
title location producer you have to see
how they made the PDF in the format and
there's usually quite a lot bundled in
that that people don't in actual fact
there's been some interesting research
done recently out of France who looked
at exactly this issue the the Privacy
issue uh for documents published by
national security agencies and and what
you could learn and this goes to more
than just the file properties but if I
if you embed a photo from your iPhone
into a PDF that all the magical
properties of your iPhone are inside the
jpeg inside the PDF and that might
include your your model number your
serial number maybe your name probably
the GPS coordinates of your of where the
photo was taken so you can well imagine
that if you are you know if you're
working in an industry that has
secrecy and privacy has a as a primary
concern then there's a lot more than
just the PDF you need to worry about
there's all the embedded internals you
know the fonts
um maybe editing markups that have
happened in in the course of publishing
a document you want to make sure they're
all scrubbed out and as I said PDF has
all this capability built into it but
unfortunately people still seem to uh
cut the corner what sort of things can
you embed in a PDF so technically and
this is one of the the security issues
is you can embed anything you can attach
and you know some of the very early
attacks you know back in the in the 90s
where people just attached the virus
payload you know a.com file or dot XE
file or a you know nowadays it'd
probably be a Powershell script or
something like that
you can just attach that to a PDF file
there's a thing called a file attachment
annotation which you can think about it
as a little paperclip icon that you
might see on your page
and obviously if a user then double
clicks that and detaches that file then
that can do all manner of nasty things
and there's certainly been things in the
past where people said I've attached you
know my favorite photo but the photos
actually called
photo.exe and users aren't always aware
what what these extensions mean and they
double click the file and instead of
opening their photo application it runs
in a malicious program and and that is
one of the security issues of PDF is it
is what we refer to as a container
format it can contain
anything basically you can embed other
things inside PDFs and like you said a
minute ago
where you think you've redacted
something I've got a graphic on the top
that could be you masquerading a button
to say you know click this to pay the
invoice online or something but it takes
you and you download the payload yes um
and certainly been tricks I mean I've
seen PDFs which masquerade as a website
so for the naive user who opens their
PDF viewer you know maybe they'll try
and push their uh PDF viewer into full
screen mode so you can't see that it's
PDF viewer and they'll be the you know
the login account from for a bank and
ask you to enter your username and
password and in the background that
button's actually sending that password
to you know to a malicious website for
mining or whatever
so I mean I guess it's the same thing
that that happens in emails people doing
the same thing you know phishing emails
so really I don't think there's you know
there are things that are unique to PDF
but realistically it's you know whatever
you can do in HTML and email you can do
with PDF because again the content flows
smoothly between these formats and
that's the whole point of the format in
a way
so criminals are just using PDF as
another another container form of attack
really like yes I mean yeah and there
certainly are other things now now the
the probably the most well-known attack
factor that gets used in PDF is
Javascript so PDF internally can can
have JavaScript just like an HTML web
page can have JavaScript
but obviously because PDFs are
Standalone and browsers are very
complicated pieces of software
then you know there can be bugs in the
implementations and the JavaScript is
providing a means by which an attacker
can leverage a bug you know and exploit
it to gain control of your computer or
or you know do whatever it wants to do
and that is why in today's world I think
all PDF fuels I would hope shipped with
their JavaScript disabled by default
so you need to enable it now obviously
with today's attackers the first
phishing attack is probably to get you
to try and enable that JavaScript so the
subsequent email attachment will then
have the malicious payload attached and
that's a sort of I think a fairly common
kind of thing especially in the
corporate world where targeted attacks
may be more common than the original
intent for
embedding these types of things with
JavaScript there or something in
particular or was it just you could
embed code to do something what would
you use that for to leave you along a
form in a PDF or something you know when
you're filling out has to do with data
validation and forms it's it's really
that that's the history of it it was I
think it was added in
the mid 90s 96 or something like that
the PDF 1.3 so you know a long long time
ago but specifically to support flexible
business forms and in those days you
have to remember HTML forms were were
not very good and PDF forms were much
richer and you know there's histories of
you know tax agencies you know you're
filling out things with forms you know
using PDF forms as a way of you know
doing very complicated things nowadays
you'd probably do an online form
uh but the history of PDF was yeah
people wanted Rich forms where you could
validate some data and update Fields if
you change this it would up to calculate
the tax and update that field and all
this kind of stuff and rather than try
and do it declaratively JavaScript was
chosen but having said that uh one of
the technical working groups inside the
PDFs Association is currently looking at
an alternative declarative technology to
JavaScript for the form solution uh
based on a concept or a technology
called Json script
okay and that
this embedding events is that similar to
how you can
do digital signatures on a PDF or you
know prove and validate they've not been
tampered with and all sorts kind of so a
digital signature you can think of as
like a hardened shell around a PDF file
so you use it you know a cryptographic
hash you calculate the contents the hash
of the PDF file and then you include
that in the PDF file and it effectively
creates this hardened shell and if
anyone changes a byte inside that
hardened shell then you can detect that
it's been tampered within you can
display the appropriate warning
of course the Assumption there is that
your software is actually bothering to
validate digital signatures and a lot of
software unfortunately doesn't bother to
validate digital signatures it just says
there's a digital signature and gives
you no indication as to whether it's
valid or invalid or you know whether
there's been any time so this would be
like an object around the PDF object
the same like a container and Docker
where you can create a heart to see if
it's being tampered yeah but
conceptually yes it's done a little bit
differently internally but conceptually
yes it's it's that sort of uh that have
the hash checks yeah is checking
I mean I've always been thinking that
you know it's kind of the experience
that we're all now grown accustomed to
the green padlock in our browsers and
really PDF needs I think the same thing
that that all our PDF viewers need to be
able to give us the green padlock when
we get an untampered
PDF file with uh you know digital
signature gives us that green padlock
and if the file's been tampered then
obviously there's a red padlock and lots
of flashing lights
because not saying anything can make
people assume it must be okay and maybe
it's not okay could we explore how a
digital signature works it's incredibly
complicated I would suggest something
much yeah but one thing I will say
though is that the pdf2 standard and
actually a few of our new extensions
about to be published are introducing a
whole lot of new technology in this
space elliptical curve signatures and
picking up on curves that have been
standardized in various countries around
the world we have integrity mechanisms
what are known as Max and we've got some
articles on our website which can
explain what these features are and how
they are slightly different
um but there's a lot of different things
we we have time stamp signatures as well
as what maybe you conventionally think
of as like a wedding signature like you
know up from a person
but a timestamp signature gives you a a
proof that a document existed at a point
in time in a particular way and again
you often used in like legal workflows
and so forth so yeah I've seen that on
um DocuSign and hell are saying where
you can attach the workflow on the back
of it and it shows you such and such
open data it was created on you know
it's been viewed by I should maybe add
one other thing about the signatures and
encryption PDF is that it's also been
designed to be extensible
so there are a number of companies out
there with proprietary encryption
Solutions sort of providing like a DRM
digital Rights Management Solutions and
if you think some of the e-book
Solutions are also based on PDF using
effectively the same kinds of Technology
thank you just to round off this last
section
can you take us through what the DARPA
funded safe docs project is yeah so I'm
a principal investigator for the
association on the safe docs program so
safe docs is a program that was looking
at as you said in the intro an
intersection of cyber security formal
methods from the research side input
parsing and file formats
and what makes this interesting is we've
had a lot of progress in sort of
protocols and and applying formal
methods and formal verifications to you
know certain protocols that are used on
the web but file formats tend to be much
larger and much more complex so this is
a really difficult problem to solve
each user's field of research known as
language theoretic security or langsac
and what does this mean well it really
means when you think about what a
vulnerability is a vulnerability is
really an input that a programmer did
not expect and that goes for almost any
vulnerability at some point the
attacker's been able to look at the code
or work out that if I just slip this
past this you know this check you've got
here then the next check will
misinterpret this and I can get control
or I can crash your program or whatever
the side effect is so if we can somehow
make it so that the the input checking
the the parsing of inputs is provably
correct then pretty much vulnerability
has become a thing of the past and this
has been possible as I say with certain
very important protocols on the web been
some great work out of Microsoft and a
few other groups as well publicized but
in the terms of file formats this is a
new and challenging problem and
especially in something as complicated
as PDF
so what safe docs has been doing is
looking at this problem from from a file
format and PDF was chosen primarily
because of its ubiquity it's important
to you know just general government and
and business and organizations and sort
of National Security
and so
we've tackled the problem in trying to
develop a formalism of PDF now
we haven't quite got there yet uh but
we've certainly had some great outcomes
we now have the first machine readable
model of the PDF object model which is
sits besides the specification so the
specification is written in English
and in the iso Community we might spend
an hour you know finally crafting an
English sentence with all the nuances
that we as experts understand about PDF
but of course for for an average reader
who's not a PDF expert but still needs
to read the spec they may not pick up on
that nuances so having a machine
readable spec where we all get a common
understanding both humans and machines
is really important is the PDF document
object model easy to explain in a
sentence or is that a major part of the
spec it's pretty easy so basically PDFs
are made up of these things called
objects and there are nine basic object
types you've got the usual you know
names numbers strings
and then we also have more complex
objects arrays of objects so very you
know programmers will know what arrays
are and dictionaries
and it's generally dictionaries have
keys in them and then the value of that
key will be maybe another dictionary so
you have a page key in the in the value
of that diction of that key is a
dictionary which is the page dictionary
and that will have the media box the
size of the page it'll have the content
that goes on the page and maybe it'll
have the page label or lots of other
information about the page so you can
see how this sort of builds up a
document object model exactly like would
be an HTML obviously different syntax
and what the the model that we've
developed the Arlington PDF model is is
basically converts this into a set of
tab separated files so they're just text
files very easy to parse and read you
can load them into jupyter notebooks or
anything like that and you can
understand
for each key the data Integrity
relationships its relationships to other
objects in the PDF model you know when
it's required when it's not required
when it was in what version of PDF it
was introduced maybe what version it was
deprecated in
you can understand whether it is an
integer and if it's an integer maybe
what the range of values are
or if it's a a string maybe what type of
string it has to be whether it can be a
Unicode string or an ASCII string or a
byte string which is just a random
sequence of bytes so it provides a lot
more detail and you don't have to Wade
through the PDF spec and you do have to
remember the PDF species 30 years old
and I can only imagine how many editors
have had to go in the PDF spec before
Duff and myself
so this gives us hopefully a much
stronger Baseline on which we can then
move forward in formalizing PDF and
providing
a common sort of machine readable
understandable version and you don't
really have to be such a expert in
understanding ISO specs thank you I'll
make sure that gets linked to in the
show notes as well just to close off the
section
could either yourself be your deaf give
me your top three tips on PDF security
if that makes sense so I think there's
it's pretty much the same for for email
and web browsing so first of all always
use up-to-date PDF software and
primarily here I'm talking about your
viewers you know your viewing software
your your software you use to interact
with your PDF files use up-to-date
software it itself will be updated for
its own patches and vulnerabilities but
because PDF is such a complex
specification it depends on many other
libraries jpeg parsing libraries XML
parsing libraries color processing
libraries Unicode processing libraries
and obviously all those libraries also
have their own series of security flaws
so using up-to-date software should be
the number one thing just you know patch
your software obviously the second one
is be careful as to where your PDFs come
from you know majority of PDFs probably
come through through email and the other
places obviously in websites and you
should be careful when you're clicking
on on PDFs you know are you trusting
this website we don't just rely on the
fact that's PDF it can't be that bad
unfortunately that's not true anymore
and it you know sometimes it might only
be a phishing EMR but still it's
something to be aware of and the last
one is always just use up-to-date
antivirus and anti-malware software on
your computer systems all the good
software nowadays will be checking PDFs
for for known malware just like the same
software we'll check websites for you
know looking for JavaScript fingerprints
and so forth it does the same thing with
PDFs it can look inside the PDFs and
find the the known malware and of course
as we've said before if you're redacting
please please use proper redaction
software and read the manual thank you
one other question I want to Chuck in
here
what are some of the most unusual or
unknown things you can do with the PDF
maybe some things that are in the spec
but you don't really see you can have a
PDF file that's a square kilometer yeah
right you can have a one-to-one scale I
believe Peter there's a one-to-one uh
scale PDF of the Tokyo
sewage system as I recall never seen it
but because it's got the size embedded
in it and it will open up pdf is the
size of Tokyo wow so I guess the other
thing that's interesting is maps and PDF
so with a map and PDF you can measure
you can drag out a line and trace a
cursor and it'll tell you how long
something is now this doesn't have to be
a map you can use an electron microscope
and you can get it in microns a PDF has
a full sort of 2D 3D measurement
capability built in
I've also seen people write games in PDF
both using JavaScript and something as
simple as just you know like a thousand
page document in each page at the bottom
has a button and you pick the button the
action you want to do and it takes you
to a different page so some people have
been very very creative with PDFs cool
thank you I think we've done a great job
of what covering our PDF is or is it PDF
or rpdf
so our PDF thing you download and PDF is
a standard or how would you like me to
say that I think it's just PDF it's in
common parlance it's epdf I think we
don't do it ourselves or anyone else any
favors when we get pedantic over the
over the uh the terminology yeah so it's
characteristically epdf yes
so yeah we've done a great job of
covering what PDF is associated security
concerns and how to make them but if
there was one thing you'd like a
software engineer to remember from our
show what would you like it to be you
can have two things one each I think for
mine it would be that remember that PDF
is an international
standard developed in an open
consensus-based Forum it hasn't been
proprietary since 2008 and that's 14
years ago the standard really has moved
on
and it really does sit beside HTML if
you if you need paginated content or
delivery of invoices or purchase orders
then you should be looking at PDF as an
alternative don't make your users have
to sort of fight
to create something that they can put in
their archive system provide a solution
for them and I think PDF is as good as
it gets nowadays and maybe there'll be
something better in the future but today
it's PDF I would answer the question in
a with a similar answer but with a
slightly different emphasis with HTML
you have broadly speaking and experience
you know you have content and CSS and
the browser server and it all comes
together at a particular moment in time
and the end user sitting at a desktop or
holding their phone they get to see
something and it includes Dynamic
content or ad that was served or
whatever it is it's an experience PDF on
the other hand is a record
it persists and I can share it with you
I can deliver it to you and you'll have
confidence that you won't just share the
experience that I have when I wrote it
you'll share that experience we'll share
that common understanding down to the
exact placement of every letter we'll
share that common understanding for
every single user whoever opens that
file down Downstream
so these are they're deeply as Peter
said they're deeply complementary
formats that HTML and PDF on the one
hand you have something that comes
together to deliver what people need at
that moment and on the other hand we
have something that persists over time
and is exceptionally reliable and they
work together they they don't compete at
all certainly a PDF is overused and does
some and people use it for some things
that probably they should be using HTML
for certainly HTML is is often used to
deliver records of particular
transactions or other kinds of events
that could probably be better delivered
as PDF because people are looking to
maintain that information over time or
across Computing systems there are
extraordinary of course capabilities and
advantages in both formats and they
complement each other for a wide variety
of business processes and I think rather
than think in terms of one or the other
in the modern era it's really about you
do things in HTML very frequently they
need to be stored or saved or in the
format in which they were originally
viewed and PDF is appropriate thank you
obviously people can follow you both on
Twitter I've got your accounts but how
else would you like people to get in
touch if they have questions you can
certainly reach us via email Twitter of
course works and PDF Association of
pdfa.org is a great way to get in touch
thank you and also GitHub as well if you
have if you're on the technical side
then we do have a GitHub presence as
well yeah I'll put that in the show
notes I've started most of your stuff
that's out there too Peter and Duff
thank you for coming on the show it's
been a real pleasure this is Gavin Henry
for software engineering radio thank you
for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening
[Music]
foreign